Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...
And provided by...
Last time, we argued about the case
of the Queen versus Dudley and Stevens.
The lifeboat case. The case of cannibalism at sea.
And with the arguments about the lifeboat in mind,
the arguments for and against what
Dudley and Stevens did in mind,
let's turn back to the philosophy,
the utilitarian philosophy of Jeremy Bentham.
Bentham was born in England in 1748.
At the age of 12, he went to Oxford.
At 15, he went to London.
At 16, he went to law school.
He was admitted to the bar at
age 19, but he never practiced law.
Instead, he devoted his life
to jurisprudence and moral philosophy.
Last time, we began to
consider Bentham's version of utilitarianism.
The main idea is simply stated, and it's this.
The highest principle of morality,
whether personal or political morality,
is to maximize the general
welfare, or the collective happiness,
or the overall balance of pleasure over pain.
In a phrase, maximize utility.
Bentham arrives at this principle
by the following line of reasoning.
We're all governed by pain and pleasure.
They are our sovereign masters.
And so any moral system
has to take account of them.
How best to take account?
By maximizing.
And this leads to the principle of
the greatest good for the greatest number.
What exactly should we maximize?
Bentham tells us, happiness, or more precisely, utility.
Maximizing utility is a principle not only for individuals,
but also for communities and for legislators.
What, after all, is a community?
Bentham asks.
It's the sum of the individuals who comprise it.
And that's why, in deciding the best policy,
in deciding what the law should be,
in deciding what's just,
citizens and legislators should ask themselves the question,
if we add up all
of the benefits of this policy,
and so on,
and subtract all of the costs,
the right thing to do is the one that maximizes
the balance of happiness over suffering.
That's what it means to maximize utility.
Now, today, I want to see
whether you agree or disagree with it.
And it often goes, this utilitarian logic,
under the name of cost-benefit analysis,
which is used by companies
and by governments all the time.
And what it involves is placing a value,
usually a dollar value, to stand for utility
on the costs and the benefits of various proposals.
Recently, in the Czech Republic,
there was a proposal to
increase the excise tax on smoking.
Philip Morris, the tobacco company,
does huge business in the Czech Republic.
They commissioned a study, a cost-benefit analysis,
of smoking in the Czech Republic.
And what their cost-benefit analysis found
was the government gains by having Czech citizens smoke.
Now, how do they gain?
It's true that there are negative effects
to the public finance of the Czech government,
because there are increased healthcare costs
for people who develop smoking-related diseases.
On the other hand, there were positive effects,
and those were added up on
the other side of the ledger.
The positive effects included, for the most part,
the various tax revenues that the government derives
from the sale of cigarette products,
but it also included healthcare savings to the government
when people die early,
pension savings, you don't have
to pay pensions for as long,
and also savings in housing costs for the elderly.
And when all of the
costs and benefits were added up,
the Philip Morris study found
that there is a net public finance gain
in the Czech Republic of $147 million.
And given the savings in
housing and healthcare and pension costs,
the government enjoys the savings of over $1,200
for each person who dies prematurely due to smoking.
Cost-benefit analysis.
Now,
those among you who are defenders of utilitarianism
may think that this is an unfair test.
Philip Morris was pilloried in the press
and they issued an apology for this heartless calculation.
You may say that what's missing here
is something that the utilitarian can easily incorporate,
namely,
the value to the person and to the families
of those who die from lung cancer.
What about the value of life?
Some cost-benefit analyses incorporate
a measure for the value of life.
One of the most famous of these
involved the Ford Pinto case.
Did any of you read about that?
This was back in the 1970s.
Do you remember what the Ford Pinto was,
that kind of car? Anybody?
It was a small car, a subcompact car, very popular.
But it had one problem,
which is the fuel tank was
at the back of the car,
and in rear collisions the fuel tank exploded.
And some people were killed,
and some severely injured.
Victims of these injuries took Ford to court to sue.
And in the court case it turned out
that Ford had long been a fan of the car,
and that Ford had been a fan of the car
since known about the vulnerable fuel tank,
and had done a cost-benefit analysis
to determine whether it would be worth it
to put in a special shield
that would protect the fuel tank
and prevent it from exploding.
They did a cost-benefit analysis.
The cost per part
to increase the safety of the Pinto,
they calculated at $11 per part.
And here's,
this was the cost-benefit analysis
that emerged in the trial.
$11 per part
at 12.5 million cars and trucks
came to a total cost of $137 million
to improve the safety.
But then they calculated the benefits
of spending all this money on a safer car.
And they counted 180 deaths,
and they assigned a dollar value,
$200,000 per death.
180 injuries,
And then the cost to repair,
the replacement cost for 2,000 vehicles
that would be destroyed without the safety device,
$700 per vehicle.
So the benefits
turned out to be only
$49.5 million.
And so they didn't install the device.
Needless to say,
when this memo
of the Ford Motor Company's
cost-benefit analysis came out in the trial,
it appalled the jurors
who awarded a huge settlement.
Is this a counterexample
to the utilitarian idea of calculating?
Ford included a measure of the value of life.
Now, who here wants to defend
cost-benefit analysis
from this apparent counterexample?
Who has a defense?
Or do you think this completely destroys
the whole utilitarian calculus?
Yes.
Well, I think that, once again,
they've made the same mistake
that they did,
that they assigned a dollar value to human life.
And once again,
they failed to take account things like
suffering and emotional losses by the families.
I mean, families lost earnings,
but they also lost a loved one.
And that is more valued than $200,000.
Right.
And wait, wait, wait.
That's good.
What's your name?
Julia Roto.
So if 200,000, Julie,
is too low a figure,
because it doesn't include the loss of a loved one
and the loss of those years of life,
what would be, what do you think,
would be a more accurate number?
I don't believe I could give a number.
I think that this sort of analysis
shouldn't be applied to issues of human life.
I think it can't be used monetarily.
So they didn't just put too low a number,
Julie says.
They were wrong to try
to put any number at all.
All right, let's hear someone who...
You have to adjust your position.
You have to adjust for inflation.
All right.
Fair enough.
So what would the number be now?
This was 30, this was 35 years ago.
$2 million.
You would put $2 million.
And what's your name?
Wojtek says we have to allow for inflation.
We should be more generous.
Then would you be satisfied
that this is the right
way of thinking about the question?
I guess, unfortunately, it is.
For there needs to be a number put somewhere.
Like, I'm not sure what that number would be,
but I do agree that there could possibly be
a number put on human life.
All right.
So Wojtek says,
and here he disagrees with Julie.
Julie says we can't put a number on human life.
For the purpose of a cost-benefit analysis.
Wojtek says we have to,
because we have to make decisions somehow.
What do other people think about this?
Is there anyone prepared
to defend cost-benefit analysis here?
As accurate, as desirable?
Yes?
Go ahead.
I think that if Ford and other car companies
didn't use cost-benefit analysis,
they'd eventually go out of business
because they wouldn't be able to be profitable.
And millions of people wouldn't
be able to use their cars
to get to jobs, to put food on the table,
to feed their children.
So I think that if cost-benefit analysis isn't employed,
the greater good is sacrificed in this case.
All right.
Let me ask, what's your name?
Raul.
There was recently a study done about cell phone use
by a driver when people are driving a car.
And there's a debate whether that should be banned.
Yeah.
And the figure was that some 2,000 people die
as a result of accidents each year using cell phones.
And yet, the cost-benefit analysis,
which was done by the
Center for Risk Analysis at Harvard,
found that if you look at
the benefits of the cell phone use
and you put some value on the life,
it comes out about the same.
Because of the enormous economic benefit
of enabling people to take advantage of their time,
not waste time, be able to make deals
and talk to friends and so on while they're driving.
Doesn't that suggest that it's a mistake
to try to put monetary
figures on questions of human life?
Well, I think that if the great majority of people
try to derive maximum utility out of a service
like using cell phones,
and the convenience that cell phones provide,
that sacrifice is necessary for satisfaction to occur.
You're an outright utilitarian.
Yes. Okay.
All right. Then one last question, Raul.
Okay.
And I put this to Wojtek.
What dollar figure should be put on human life
to decide whether to ban the use of cell phones?
Well, I don't want to arbitrarily
calculate a figure.
I mean, right now, I think that...
You want to take it under advisement?
Yeah, I'll take it under advisement.
But what, roughly speaking, would it be?
You've got 2,300 deaths.
You've got to assign a dollar value
to know whether you want to prevent those deaths
by banning the use of cell phones in cars.
Okay.
So what would your hunch be?
How much?
A million? Two million?
Two million was Wojtek's figure.
Yeah.
Is that about right?
Maybe a million.
A million?
Yeah.
You know the...
That's good. Thank you.
Okay.
So these are some of the controversies
that arise these days from cost-benefit analysis,
especially those that involve placing a dollar value
on everything to be added up.
Well, now I want to turn to your objections.
To your objections not necessarily
to cost-benefit analysis,
but to the cost-benefit analysis specifically,
because that's just one version
of the utilitarian logic in practice today,
but to the theory as a whole,
to the idea that the right thing to do,
the just basis for policy and law,
is to maximize utility.
How many disagree with the utilitarian...
approach to law and to the common good?
How many agree with it?
So more agree than disagree.
So let's hear from the critics.
Yes.
My main issue with it is that I feel like
you can't say that just because someone's in the minority,
what they want and need is less valuable
than someone who's in the majority.
So I guess I have an issue with the idea
that the greatest good for the greatest number is okay,
because there's still...
What about the people who are in the lesser number?
Like, it's not fair to them.
They didn't have any say
in where they wanted to be.
All right. That's an interesting objection.
You're worried about the effect on the minority.
Yes.
What's your name, by the way?
Anna.
Who has an answer to Anna's worry
about the effect on the minority?
What do you say to Anna?
She said that the minorities value less.
I don't think that's the case,
because individually the minority's value
is just the same as the individual of the majority.
It's just that the numbers outweigh the minority.
And, I mean, at a certain
point, you have to make a decision,
and I'm sorry for the minority,
but sometimes it's for the general, for the greater good.
For the greater good. Anna, what do you say?
What's your name?
Youngda.
What do you say to Youngda?
Youngda says you just have to add up people's preferences,
and those in the minority do have their preferences weighed.
Can you give an example of
the kind of thing you're worried about
when you say you're worried about utilitarianism
violating the concern or respect due the minority?
Okay.
Can you give an example?
So, well, with any of
the cases that we've talked about,
like for the shipwreck one,
I think the boy who was eaten still had
as much of a right
to live as the other people,
and just because he was the minority in that case,
the one who maybe had less
of a chance to keep living,
that doesn't mean that the others
automatically have a right to eat him
just because it would give a greater
amount of people a chance to live.
So there may be certain
rights that the minority members have,
that the individual has,
that shouldn't be traded off for the sake of utility.
Yes, Anna?
Youngda, this would be a test for you.
Back in ancient Rome,
they threw Christians to the
lions in the Colosseum for sport.
If you think how the utilitarian calculus would go,
yes, the Christian thrown to
the lions suffers enormous, excruciating pain.
But look at the collective ecstasy of the Romans.
Youngda?
Well, in that time,
in modern day of time,
to give a number to the
happiness given to the people watching,
I don't think any policy maker would say
the suffering of one person is much, much,
in comparison to the happiness gained.
No, but you have to admit
that if there were enough
Romans delirious enough with happiness,
it would outweigh even the most excruciating pain
of a handful of Christians thrown to the lion.
So we really have here
two different objections to utilitarianism.
One has to do with whether utilitarianism,
adequately respects individual rights or minority rights.
And the other has to do
with the whole idea of aggregating utility
or preferences or values.
Is it possible to aggregate all
values to translate them into dollar terms?
There was, in the 1930s,
a very important argument.
And a psychologist who tried
to address this second question,
he tried to prove what utilitarianism assumes,
that it is possible to translate all goods, all values,
all human concerns into a single uniform measure.
And he did this by conducting
a survey of young recipients of relief.
This was in the 1930s.
And he asked them,
he gave them a list of unpleasant experiences.
how much would you have to
be paid to undergo the following experiences?
And he kept track.
For example,
how much would you have to be paid
to have one upper front tooth pulled out?
Or how much would you have to be
paid to have one little toe cut off?
Or to eat a live earthworm six inches long?
Or to live the rest of
your life on a farm in Kansas?
Or to choke a stray cat
to death with your bare hands?
Now what do you suppose was
the most expensive item on that list?
Kansas?
You're right, it was Kansas.
For Kansas, people said they'd have to be paid $300,000.
What do you think,
what do you think,
what do you think was the next most expensive?
Not the cat.
Not the tooth.
Not the toe.
The worm.
People said you'd have to pay
them $100,000 to eat the worm.
What do you think was the least expensive item?
Not the cat.
The tooth.
During the Depression, people were willing to
have their tooth pulled for only $4,500.
Now, here's what Thorndike concluded from his study.
Any want or satisfaction which exists, exists
in some amount and is therefore measurable.
The life of a dog or a cat or
a chicken consists of appetites, cravings, desires, and their gratifications.
So does the life of human beings,
though the appetites and desires are more complicated.
But what about Thorndike's study?
Does it support Bentham's idea that all goods, all values,
are captured according to a single uniform measure of value?
Or does the preposterous character of
those different items on the list
suggest the opposite conclusion that maybe,
whether we're talking about life or Kansas or the worm,
maybe the things we value and cherish can't be
captured according to a single uniform measure of value.
And if they can't, what are the
consequences for the utilitarian theory of morality?
That's a question we'll continue with next time.
All right, now let's take
the other part of the poll.
Which is the highest experience or pleasure?
How many say Shakespeare?
How many say Fear Factor?
No, you can't be serious. Really?
Last time, last time we began to consider some objections.
To Jeremy Bentham's version of utilitarianism.
People raised two objections in the discussion we had.
The first was the objection, the claim,
that utilitarianism, by concerning itself with
the greatest good for the greatest number,
fails adequately to respect individual values.
Today we have debates about torture and terrorism.
Suppose a suspected terrorist
was apprehended on September 10th.
And you had reason to believe that the suspect had crucial
information about an impending terrorist attack that would kill over 3,000 people.
And you couldn't extract the information.
Would it be just to torture
the suspect to get the information?
Or do you say no, there is a
categorical moral duty of respect for individual rights?
In a way, we're back to the questions
we started with about trolley cars and organ transplants.
So that's the first issue.
And you remember we considered
some examples of cost-benefit analysis.
But a lot of people were unhappy with cost-benefit analysis
when it came to placing
a dollar value on human life.
And so that led us to the second objection.
It questioned whether it's possible to translate all values
into a single uniform measure of value.
It asks, in other words,
whether all values are commensurable.
Let me give you one other example of an experience.
This actually is a true story.
It comes from personal experience.
That raises a question, at least, about whether all
values can be translated without loss into utilitarian terms.
Some years ago, when I was a
graduate student, I was at Oxford in England,
and they had men's and women's colleges.
They weren't yet mixed.
And the women's colleges had
rules against overnight male guests.
By the 1970s, these rules
were rarely enforced and easily violated.
Or so I was told.
By the late 1970s, when I was
there, pressure grew to relax these rules,
and it became the subject of debate
among the faculty at St. Anne's College,
which was one of these all-women's colleges.
The older women on the faculty were traditionalists.
They were opposed to change on conventional moral grounds.
But times had changed, and they were embarrassed
to give the true groundwork.
The men's colleges were not the only ones
to change on conventional moral grounds for their objection.
And so they translated
their arguments into utilitarian terms.
If men stay overnight, they argued
the costs to the college will increase.
How, you might wonder?
Well, they'll want to take baths, and
that'll use up hot water, they said.
Furthermore, they argued, we'll have
to replace the mattresses more often.
They met these arguments
by adopting the following compromise.
Each woman could have a maximum
of three overnight male guests each week.
They didn't say whether it had to
be the same one or three different.
Provided, and this was the compromise,
provided the guest paid 50 pence
to defray the cost to the college.
The next day,
the national headline in the national newspaper read,
St. Anne's girls, 50 pence a night.
Another illustration of the
difficulty of translating all values,
in this case a certain idea of virtue,
into utilitarian terms.
So, that's all to illustrate
the second objection to utilitarianism,
at least the part of that objection
that questions whether utilitarianism is right
to assume that we can assume the uniformity of value,
the commensurability of all values,
and translate all moral
considerations into dollars or money.
But there is a second aspect to this worry
about aggregating values and preferences.
Why should we weigh all preferences that people have
without assessing whether they're
good preferences or bad preferences?
Shouldn't we distinguish between
higher pleasures and lower pleasures?
Now, part of the appeal of not making any claims
about qualitative distinctions,
about the worth of people's preferences,
part of the appeal is
that it is nonjudgmental and egalitarian.
The Benthamite utilitarian says,
everybody's preferences count,
and they count regardless of what people want,
regardless of what makes different people happy.
For Bentham, all that matters, you'll remember,
are the intensity and the
duration of a pleasure or pain.
The so-called higher pleasures or nobler virtues
are simply those, according to Bentham,
that produce stronger, longer pleasure.
He had a famous phrase to express this idea.
The quantity of pleasure being equal,
pushpin is as good as poetry.
What was pushpin?
It was some kind of a child's game,
like tiddlywinks.
Pushpin is as good as poetry, Bentham says.
And lying behind this idea, I think,
is the claim, the intuition,
that it's a presumption to judge
whose pleasures are intrinsically
higher or worthier or better.
And there is something attractive in this refusal to judge.
After all, some people like Mozart, others, Madonna.
Some people like ballet, others, bowling.
Who's to say, Bentham might argue,
who's to say which of these pleasures,
whose pleasures, are higher, worthier, nobler than others?
But is that right?
This refusal to make qualitative distinctions.
Can we altogether dispense with the idea
that certain things we take pleasure in
are better or worthier than others?
Think back to the case
of the Romans and the Colosseum.
One thing that troubled people about that practice
is that it seemed to
violate the rights of the Christian.
Another way of objecting to what's going on there
is that the pleasure that the Romans take
in this bloody spectacle,
should that pleasure, which is a base kind of corrupt,
degrading pleasure,
should that even be valorized or weighed
in deciding what the general welfare is?
So here are the objections to Bentham's utilitarianism.
And now we turn to someone who tried to respond
to those objections,
a later-day utilitarian, John Stuart Mill.
So what we need to examine now
is whether John Stuart Mill had a convincing reply
to these objections to utilitarianism.
John Stuart Mill was born in 1806.
His father, James Mill, was a disciple of Bentham's.
And James Mill set about giving his son,
John Stuart Mill, a model education.
He was a child prodigy, John Stuart Mill.
He knew Latin at the age of, sorry,
Greek at the age of three, Latin at eight,
and age 10, he wrote a history of Roman law.
At age 20, he had a nervous breakdown.
This left him in a depression for five years.
But at age 25, what helped
lift him out of this depression
is that he met Harriet Taylor.
She and Mill got married.
They lived happily ever after.
And it was under her influence
that John Stuart Mill tried to humanize utilitarianism.
What Mill tried to do was to see
whether the utilitarian calculus could be enlarged
and modified to accommodate humanitarian concerns
like the concern to respect individual rights
and also to address the distinction
between higher and lower pleasures.
In 1859, Mill wrote a famous book on liberty,
the main point of which was the importance
of defending individual rights and minority rights.
And in 1861,
toward the end of his life,
he wrote the book we
read as part of this course,
Utilitarianism.
He makes it clear that utility
is the only standard of morality,
in his view.
So he's not challenging Bentham's premise.
He's affirming it.
He says very explicitly,
the sole evidence it is possible to produce
that anything is desirable
is that people actually do desire it.
So he stays with the idea
that de facto, actual, empirical desires
are the only basis for moral judgment.
But then, on page eight,
also in chapter two,
he argues that it is possible for a utilitarian
to distinguish higher from lower pleasures.
Now, those of you who have read Mill already,
how, according to him,
is it possible to draw that distinction?
How can a utilitarian
distinguish qualitatively higher pleasures
from lesser ones, base ones, unworthy ones?
Yes?
If you've tried both of them,
and you prefer the higher one naturally, always.
That's great. That's right.
What's your name?
John.
So, as John points out,
Mill says, here's the test.
Since we can't step outside
actual desires, actual preferences,
that would violate utilitarian premises.
The only test
of whether a pleasure is higher or lower
is whether someone who has experienced both
would prefer it.
And here, in chapter two,
we see the passage where Mill makes the point
that John just described.
Of two pleasures, if there be one to which all,
or almost all, who have experience of both,
give a decided preference,
irrespective of any feeling of
moral obligation to prefer it,
in other words, no outside, no independent standard,
then that is the more desirable pleasure.
What do people think about that argument?
Does that...
Does it succeed?
How many think that it does succeed?
Of arguing within utilitarian terms
for a distinction between higher and lower pleasures?
How many think it doesn't succeed?
I want to hear your reasons.
But before we give the reasons,
let's do an experiment
of Mill's claim.
In order to do this experiment,
we're going to look at three short excerpts
of popular entertainment.
The first one is a Hamlet soliloquy.
It'll be followed by two other experiences.
See what you think.
What a piece of work is a man.
How noble in reason.
How infinite in faculties.
In form and moving.
How express and admirable.
In action, how like an angel.
In apprehension, how like a god.
The beauty of the world.
The paragon of animals.
And yet to me,
what is this quintessence of dust?
Man delights not me.
Imagine a world
where your greatest fears become reality.
Ow, they're biting me!
Each show, six contestants from around the country
battle each other in three extreme stunts.
These stunts are designed to challenge the contestants
both physically and mentally.
Six contestants, three stunts,
one winner.
Yes!
Fear Factor.
Hi, diddly-ho, pedal to the metalophiles.
Landers, since when do you like anything cool?
Well, I don't care for the speed,
but I can't get enough of that safety gear.
Helmets, roll bars, caution flags.
I like the fresh air
and looking at the poor people in the infield.
I like the
I don't even have to
ask which one you like most.
The Simpsons.
How many like The Simpsons most?
How many Shakespeare?
What about Fear Factor?
How many preferred Fear Factor?
Really?
People overwhelmingly like The Simpsons better
than Shakespeare.
All right, now let's take
the other part of the poll.
Which is the highest experience or pleasure?
How many say Shakespeare?
How many say Fear Factor?
No, you can't be serious.
Really?
What?
All right, go ahead.
You can say it.
I found that one the most entertaining.
I know, but which do you think was the worthiest,
the noblest experience?
I know you found it the most entertaining.
If something is good just because it is pleasurable,
what does it matter whether you
have sort of an abstract idea
of whether it is good
by someone else's sense or not?
All right, so you come
down in the straight Benthamite side.
Who's the best?
Who's to judge?
And why should we judge?
Apart from just registering
and aggregating de facto preferences.
All right, that's fair enough.
What's your name?
Nate.
Nate?
Okay, fair enough.
All right, so how many think The Simpsons is actually,
apart from liking it, is actually the higher experience?
Higher than Shakespeare.
All right, let's see the vote for Shakespeare again.
How many think Shakespeare is higher?
All right.
So why is it?
Ideally, I'd like to hear from someone.
Is there someone who thinks Shakespeare is highest,
but who preferred watching The Simpsons?
Yes.
Like, I guess just sitting watching The Simpsons,
it's entertaining because they make
jokes and they make us laugh,
but like someone has to tell
us that Shakespeare was this great writer.
We had to be taught how
to read him, how to understand him.
to kind of take in Rembrandt,
how to analyze a painting.
Well, let me, what's your name?
Anisha.
Anisha, when you say someone
told you that Shakespeare is better.
Right.
Are you accepting it on blind faith?
You voted that Shakespeare is higher
only because the culture tells you that
or teachers tell you that, or
do you actually agree with that yourself?
Well, in the sense of Shakespeare, no,
but earlier you made an example of Rembrandt.
I feel like I would enjoy reading a comic
book more than I would enjoy kind of analyzing Shakespeare.
I would enjoy reading a comic book
more than I would enjoy reading Rembrandt
because someone told me it was great, you know?
Right.
So some of this seems to be you're
suggesting a kind of cultural convention and pressure.
We're told what books, what works of art are great.
Who else?
Yes.
Although I enjoyed watching The Simpsons
more in this particular moment in Justice,
if I were to spend
the rest of my life considering
the three different video clips shown,
I would not want to spend that remainder
of my life considering the latter two clips.
I think I would derive more pleasure from
being able to branch out in my own mind,
sort of considering more deep pleasures, more deep thoughts.
And tell me your name.
Joe.
So if you had to
spend the rest of your life
on a farm in Kansas with only Shakespeare
or the collected episodes of The Simpsons,
you would prefer Shakespeare?
What do you conclude from
that about John Stuart Mill's test?
That the test of a higher pleasure is
whether people who have experienced both prefer it.
Can I cite another example briefly?
Yeah.
In biology, neurobiology last year we were
told of a rat who was tested
a particular center in the brain where
the rat was able to stimulate its brain
and cause itself intense pleasure repeatedly.
The rat did not eat or drink until it died.
So the rat was clearly experiencing intense pleasure.
Now if you ask me right now
if I would rather experience intense pleasure
or have a full lifetime of higher pleasure,
I would consider intense pleasure to be low pleasure.
I would right now enjoy intense pleasure.
But, yes I would.
I certainly would.
But over a lifetime, I think, I would
think almost a complete majority here would agree
that they would rather be a human with
higher pleasure than be that rat with intense pleasure
for a momentary period of time.
Now in answer to your question,
Right.
I think this proves that, or I won't say proves,
I think the conclusion is that Mill's theory
that when a majority of people are asked
what they would rather do,
they will answer that they would
rather engage in a higher pleasure.
So you think that this supports Mill,
you think Mill is onto something here?
I do.
Alright.
Is there anyone who disagrees with Joe
and who thinks that our experiment disproves
Mill's test?
Shows that that's not an adequate
way that you can't distinguish higher pleasures
within the utilitarian framework?
Yes.
If whatever is good is truly just whatever people prefer,
it's truly relative and there's no objective definition,
then there will be some
society where people prefer Simpsons more.
Anyone can appreciate the Simpsons,
but I think it does take
education to appreciate Shakespeare as much.
Alright.
You're saying it takes
education to appreciate higher things.
True.
Mill's point is that the higher pleasures
do require cultivation and appreciation and education.
He doesn't dispute that.
But once having been cultivated and educated,
people will see, not only see
the difference between higher and lower pleasures,
but will actually prefer the higher to the lower.
You find this famous passage from John Stuart Mill,
it is better to be a
human being dissatisfied than a pig satisfied.
Better to be Socrates dissatisfied than a fool satisfied.
And if the fool or the pig,
are of a different opinion,
it is because they only
know their side of the question.
So here you have an attempt
to distinguish higher from lower pleasures.
So going to an art museum or being a
couch potato and swilling beer watching television at home.
Sometimes Mill agrees we might succumb to the temptation
to do the latter, to be couch potatoes.
But even when we do that,
out of indolence and sloth,
we know that the pleasure we get
gazing at Rembrandts in the museum is actually higher.
Because we've experienced both.
And it is a higher pleasure gazing at Rembrandts
because it engages our higher human faculties.
What about Mill's attempt
to reply to the objection about individual rights?
In a way, he uses the same kind of argument.
And this comes out in chapter five.
He says, I dispute the pretensions of any theory
which sets up an imaginary standard of justice
not grounded on utility,
but still he considers justice grounded on utility
to be what he calls the chief part
and incomparably the most sacred
and binding part of all morality.
So justice is higher.
Individual rights are privileged.
But not for reasons
that depart from utilitarian assumptions.
Justice is a name for certain moral requirements
which, regarded collectively,
stand higher in the scale of social utility
and are therefore of more paramount obligation
than any others.
So justice is sacred, it's prior, it's privileged.
It isn't something that can easily
be traded off against lesser things.
But the reason is ultimately, Mill claims,
a utilitarian reason,
once you consider the long-run interests of humankind,
of all of us as progressive beings.
If we do justice and if we respect rights,
society as a whole will be
better off in the long run.
Well, is that convincing?
Or is Mill actually, without admitting it,
stepping outside utilitarian considerations
in arguing for qualitatively higher pleasures
and for sacred or especially important individual rights?
We haven't fully answered that question
because to answer that question in
the case of rights and justice
will require that we explore other ways,
non-utilitarian ways,
of accounting for the basis of rights.
And then asking whether they succeed.
As for Jeremy Bentham,
who launched utilitarianism
as a doctrine in moral and legal philosophy,
Bentham died in 1832 at the age of 85.
But if you go to
London, you can visit him today,
literally.
He provided in his will
that his body be preserved, embalmed, and displayed
in the University of London,
where he still presides in a glass case
with a wax head,
dressed in his actual clothing.
You see, before he died,
Bentham addressed himself
to a question consistent with his philosophy.
Of what use could a
dead man be to the living?
One use, he said, would
be to make one's corpse available
to the study of anatomy.
In the case of great philosophers,
however,
better yet,
to preserve one's physical presence
in order to inspire future generations of thinkers.
You want to see what Bentham looks like, stuffed?
Here's what he looks like.
There he is.
Now, if you look closely,
you will notice
that the embalming of his actual head
was not a success.
So they substituted a waxed head
and at the bottom, for verisimilitude,
you can actually see his actual head
on a plate.
You see it?
Right there.
So, what's the moral of the story?
The moral of the story...
By the way, they bring him
out during meetings of the board
at University College London,
and the minutes record him
as present but not voting.
Here is a philosopher,
in life and in death,
who adhered
to the principles
of his philosophy.
We'll continue with rights next time.
For more, visit justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.
They're for this right.
These investments are in the state...
BIPE
Stuff Up
Street
It's the right thing to do.
S dizung
you